Have you ever wondered if there are more
natural ways to lower your high blood
pressure, guard against Alzheimer's,
lose weight, feel better? Well, it turns
out there is. Welcome to the Nutrition
Facts podcast. I'm your host, Dr.
Michael Greger.
Today, we take a deep dive into the best
way to choose the safest and most
effective sunscreen. considered the
single most important practice for
maintaining youthful skin. The daily
application of sunscreen and taking
other protective measures like wearing a
hat. All the other things you can do for
your skin pale in comparison, especially
for those with pale skin. Up to 90% of
visible facial aging among people with
lighter skin tones is due to exposure to
sunlight. Those with darker skin are
relatively protected due to their
built-in melanin sunscreen, but they're
still affected. Sun damage in darker
skin tends to be less about wrinkles and
more about pigmentation issues such as
uneven skin tones, dark patches, and
small dark bumps on the face. Either
way, dermatologists now agree that
there's nothing more important to slow
the signs of aging than to protect your
skin from the sun. Pats like sun
exposure and smoking can make us look up
to 11 years older. And compare that to
extensive cosmetic surgery. A faceelift
and a neck lift and removing excess skin
from both upper and lower eyelids and a
forehead lift which combined can make us
look about 8 years younger. So a healthy
lifestyle may work even better.
Protecting your skin from the sun should
be a lifelong endeavor. This can involve
applying sunscreen, wearing
sunprotective clothing, hats, and
sunglasses, and avoiding direct sunlight
during the peak hours of 10:00 a.m. to 4
p.m., and instead seeking shady covered
areas. Sunbathing is frowned upon, even
with sunscreens like zinc oxide or
titanium dioxide that offer
broadspectctrum protection against both
UVA, UVB rays. We now know that other
wavelengths such as near infrared that
are not covered by sunscreens also
contribute to skin aging. Men and women
who use tanning beds appear
significantly older than those who
don't. And white women who some bathe
appear years older than they actually
are, similar to what is seen with
smoking. UVA rays are primarily
responsible for skin aging, whereas UVB
are the rays that cause sunburn, but a
broadspectctrum sunscreen covering both
is recommended since both types of UV
contribute to cancer risk. To prevent
skin cancer, the American Academy of
Dermatology recommends sunscreen with an
SPF of 30 or higher. But an SPF even as
low as 15 can help prevent skin aging.
How do we know? Because it's been put to
the test. Despite the widespread belief
that the use of sunscreen would prevent
skin aging, all we had was data on
hairless mice. That is until 10 years
ago. 900 adults were randomized either
to years of daily sunscreen use or to
continue with their own discretionary
use. It was considered unethical to
withhold protection by giving people
placebo sunscreen. In the end, 77% in
the recommended daily sunscreen group
were applying sunscreen at least 3 to 4
days per week compared with only 33% in
the discretionary use group. Would that
be enough of a difference to make a
difference? Yes. There was significantly
less skin aging in the instructed daily
use group. In fact, they suffered no
detectable increase in skin aging over
the four and a half year study. The
researchers concluded regular sunscreen
use retards skin aging in healthy
middle-aged men and women. Okay, so to
reiterate, there's nothing more
important to slow the signs of aging
than to protect your skin from the sun.
This involves avoiding direct sunlight
since there are skin aging wavelengths
not covered by sunscreens and wearing a
daily SPF 30 plus sunscreen proven to
slow aging in a randomized control
trial.
Okay, but what if you care less about
how you look and more about avoiding
cancer? Has sunscreen been similarly
proven to prevent skin cancer? Let's
find out in my next video. Does
sunscreen really prevent skin cancer?
Let's find out. Decades ago, studies
started bubbling up reporting that not
only was the use of sunscreen not found
to be protective against skin cancer,
but it was associated with significantly
elevated risk. But subsequent studies
offered the obvious explanation of this
paradox. People who use sunscreen are
more likely to be sunbathers.
That's like finding those who use
motorcycle helmets are more likely to
die on the highway. I mean, it's not
that sunscreen and helmets aren't
protective. It's just that they're
associated with engagement in risky
activities, but you don't know until you
put it to the test. Randomized control
trials have shown that regular use of
sunscreen can arrest visible signs of
skin aging, including biopsy proven
reductions in UV related skin damage.
But are there interventional trials
proving sunscreen can prevent cancer?
Yes. Organ transplant recipients are
highly susceptible to skin cancers
because they have to be given immune
suppressants to prevent organ rejection.
A group of 120 organ recipients were
equally informed about sun protection
measures, but half were given free
broadspectctrum SPF 50 plus sunscreen
for daily application to their head,
neck, forearms, and hands. After 2
years, there were nine new basil
carcinomomas in the control group versus
only two in the sunscreen group. That
sounds good, but may have just been a
fluke. In contrast, there was a highly
significant difference in the proportion
of patients who got new invasive squamic
cell carcinoma. Eight new cases in the
control group versus zero in the
sunscreen group. But wait until you hear
about what happened to their actctinic
keratossis, the precancerous growths
that can turn into skin cancer. They all
started out covered in them. A total of
191 detected in each group. In the
subsequent 24 months, the control group
developed 82 new ones. How many did the
sunscreen group develop? Negative 102.
More than 100 precancerous growths in
the sunscreen group spontaneously
regressed and vanished completely
compared to 82 new growths developing in
the control group without a single one
disappearing. Their bodies, even in
their immuno compromised state, could
heal itself once it just stopped being
bombarded with so many cancer-causing
rays. Other randomized control trials
have shown similar findings, but
generalizability is limited. The studies
all use high-risk populations, for
example, those living in subtropical
climates or with a personal history of
precancerous lesions. So cancer
prevention efficacy in the general
population be expected to be less. On
the other hand, the studies could also
have underestimated the impact since
they were relatively shortterm, not
exceeding four years, and ethically had
to allow the control group participants
to slather on their own sunscreen, which
would dilute the difference between
groups. For maximum effectiveness,
sunscreen needs to be applied properly,
which apparently rarely happens in the
real world. In a study of nearly 5,000
skiers and snowboarders, almost no one,
only about 4% were fully compliant with
sunscreen recommendations. First,
there's the amount. The FDA standard is
2 milligs per square cimeter. What does
that mean? Use the teaspoon rule. One
teaspoon for your face, head, and neck.
One for the front of your torso, another
for your back, one teaspoon for each
arm, and two teaspoons for each leg.
That's a total of 9 teaspoon. It's about
the total volume equivalent of a golf
ball or or a shot glass to help you
visualize it. Unfortunately, the average
sunscreen user may only apply a quarter
of the recommended amount. This is why
high SPF sunscreens are often
recommended, like, you know, 50 plus
SPF. Although the FDA recommends a
minimum SPF of only 15 to prevent skin
cancer, under normal consumer
conditions, even an SPF of 50 may
effectively give you only an SPF of 12.5
because most people don't put on enough.
Randomized double blind head-to-head
split face experiments where you're
randomized to apply one sunscreen to one
side of your face and another sunscreen
to the other side show that in real life
use SPF 100 plus sunscreen work
significantly better than SPF 50 plus
sunscreen. More than 50% of the
participants were sunburned more on
their SPF 50 plus side compared to only
5% on their SPF 100 plus side. Now, a
potential downside of higher SPF
sunscreens is that they could provide a
false sense of security. Those
randomized to an SPF 30 sunscreen ended
up spending more cumulative time in the
sun than those receiving an SPF 10
sunscreen as much as five times longer
in some case. What else? Well, people
tend to remember to use sunscreen on a
sunny day at the beach, but sun
protection is needed even on cloudy days
since the UV rays are not dampened as
much as visible light. There's even a
phenomenon known as cloud enhancement,
where overcast skies can sometimes
result in even more UV reaching the
Earth's surface compared to clear skies.
Sunscreen labels often suggest waiting
at least 15 minutes after application
before going outdoors. But when put to
the test, sunscreen was found to start
working immediately with the full effect
apparent by minute 10. However, if water
resistance is required, it may be
prudent to wait the full 15 to 30
minutes after application before taking
a dip. The terms waterproof or
sweatproof appear to be meaningless
marketing as no difference in retention
was noted between quoteunquote
waterproof products and those that were
merely labeled waterresistant. Both were
better than nonwater resistant products
though, which lost nearly all their
protective effects within 20 minutes of
water immersion.
The suggestion that sunscreen should be
reapplied every 2 to three hours only
applies under conditions in which it is
rinsed off by water or sweat or rubbed
off by friction from clothing or sand.
Even after allowing sunscreen to dry
first for 20 minutes, between 15 and 60%
of its protective effect can be lost
after contact with sand. Otherwise, if
the recommended amount is applied and
the sunscreen layer is not disturbed,
SPF can be maintained for as long as 8
hours.
What kind of sunscreen should you use?
Creambased is preferable to spray on
since the completeness of application is
more readily visualized. To help with
adequate coverage, spray-on sunscreen
should be rubbed on immediately after
spraying. Aerosolized sunscreens are
flammable and can combust on skin upon
exposure to an open flame, even after
the sunscreen has dried. What's more,
the safety of breathing in aerosolized
sunscreen chemicals has not been
adequately studied. Though frankly, the
same thing could be said about rubbing
them on your skin. The concerns
surrounding sunscreen safety are
three-fold. Increased intentional sun
exposure, vitamin D deficiency, and
untored effects from systemic absorption
of sunscreen chemicals.
In the 1800s, we first learned that UVB
caused sunburns and formulated
sunscreens to block it. Nearly a century
later, we learned about the contribution
of UVA. Now a full century later, we are
realizing that infrared and visible
light may also be contributing to cancer
and premature skin aging. Sunlight comes
to us in three major bands. Visible
light, ultraviolet, and infrared.
Visible light includes the colors of the
rainbow. Red, orange, yellow, green,
blue, indigo, and violet or roy g biv.
Ultraviolet UV is to the right of violet
in Roy Giv and infrared to the left of
red. Sunscreen can protect us against
the free radical damage of UV, but half
of the free radical formation in our
skin from the sun may be from the
visible or infrared spectrums which
sunscreens may not adequately cover. So
that's where sun avoidance strategies
come in. But you can imagine how shade
seeking could be undermined by the
salacement of a sunscreen security
blanket. What about vitamin D? The
theoretical concern about sunscreen
affecting vitamin D status does not seem
to manifest in the real world, likely
because the UV dose necessary for
vitamin D production is so low well
before skin turns a pinker shade.
However, concerns about the systemic
absorption of sunscreen chemicals were
underscored by the recent FDA bombshell
that not a single one of sunscreen
chemicals in current use can be
considered generally recognized as safe.
Only two active ingredients got the
green light. The two non-chemical
mineral sunscreens, titanium dioxide and
zinc oxide. The revelation was based on
a growing body of evidence that
transermal, meaning through the skin
absorption of sunscreen chemicals was
greater than we previously thought,
raising unevaluated safety concerns.
Unevaluated because we previously didn't
think so much got into our bloodstreams.
In 2019, a study published in the
Journal of the American Medical
Association found that under maximum
usage conditions over a period of days,
the blood levels of all the sunscreen
chemicals they tested exceeded the FDA
threshold that could potentially wave
further safety testing. Then in 2020,
they found that just a single
application of all the chemical
sunscreens they tested surpassed the
threshold. Now, just because they're
absorbed into our system doesn't
necessarily mean they're unsafe. It just
means they need to be tested for safety,
which the FDA determined the
multibillion dollar sunscreen industry
has so far failed to do. The FDA
concluded that two ingredients can be
considered safe, zinc oxide and titanium
dioxide, and two can be considered
unsafe, PABA and trollamine salicellate.
And the other 12 ingredients that are
currently marketed have yet to be
sufficiently safety tested. According to
a review of more than 700 sunscreen
brands, it appears PABA and Trolamine
are no longer being marketed in
sunscreens sold in the United States.
Uh, but they still may be available in
other countries. Until the data are in
on the rest of the chemical sunscreens,
I would recommend sticking to the two
mineral sunscreens. Historically,
they've tended to be thicker and wider,
which can lead to even more severe
underdosing, but newer micronized
formulations with smaller mineral
particle sizes tend to be less
noticeable. This is particularly an
issue for those with darker skin. The
average built-in SPF of black skin, also
known in the medical literature as quote
unquote ethnic skin or SOC, skin of
color, is about 13 naturally compared
with only about three for white skin.
Though there haven't been any
interventional studies on sunscreen
effectiveness for skin cancer prevention
in people with dark skin, SPF 13 is not
considered sufficient sun protection.
So, the American Academy of Dermatology
recommends regular sunscreen use with an
SPF of 30 or higher for people of all
skin types. Unfortunately, only about
12% of non-Hispanic blacks and 31% of
Hispanics report regularly using
sunscreen compared to about 44% of
non-Hispanic whites. Uh, despite this,
the incidence of melanoma, the deadliest
skin cancer, is five times lower in
Hispanics compared to whites and more
than 25 times lower among blacks.
However, the mortality rate if you do
get it is higher among African-Americans
presumed to be due from delayed
diagnosis. Okay. So, in short, only two
sunscreen active ingredients can be
considered safe at this time. And that's
the two so-called mineral sunscreens,
titanium dioxide and zinc oxide. Um
though remember in the first part of the
video talking about how that may really
only cover UV um the the ultraviolet
range um and so sun avoidance is still
important um since maybe half the free
radicals created by uh sun exposure are
from the nonovered spectrum. So
avoidance um in addition to using good
sunscreens is still important. Um,
absolutely outrageous that that safety
testing wasn't done by industry. Um, but
now they're going to be forced to. Um,
and it's about time. All right. Uh, Q&A
time. Happy to talk about anything that
came up today or any related topics of
uh, skin aging in general. Got a whole
chapter on it in uh, how not to age. Um,
and so we could bring up the the the the
pre-release sneak preview and go through
anything you'd like. Okay, let's do
this.
Okay, let me pull up the questions.
Sunscreen questions. All right. What
ingredients are the safest for lip
products containing optimal sunscreen?
So glad you answered. You can actually
get melanoma of the lip. Uh deadly skin
cancer of the lip just like you can get
skin cancer anywhere. Um and so the
safest would be the same thing. titanium
dioxide, zinc oxide, the two mineral
sunscreens for lip products as well. I'm
so glad you asked that question. People
may not um think of that. Um okay. When
returning indoors after sunscreen skin
application, is showering recommended to
prevent possible adverse issue uh issues
from sunscreen, chemical skin
absorption? What duration is safest to
have sunscreen on the screen before on
the skin before washing it off? And the
answer to that question is do not wear
chemical sunscreens because we cannot
presume them to be safe. Now, if you do
have a chemical sunscreen, would it be
better to wash it off? That's a good
question. Like, I don't know how long it
takes for that. I'd have to go back to
that study to see um how long after
application does it get absorbed.
Remember that study showed just a single
application could exceed um the levels
that uh exceed the the threshold levels
um from the FDA in terms of uh uh
needing to require toxicity testing. So
it gets into your bloodstream. Uh how
what are the kinetics of it? Like is it
like within the first hour or does it
take like eight hours or something? Um
and can you just wash it up? That's a
good question. But uh uh so that's kind
of a good kind of just kind of curiosity
question, but the answer, the true
answer is just don't use those chemical
sunscreens until we know they're safe.
Period. Okay, next up,
any contraindications? Oh, that's a
fancy doctor word. Um for I'm sorry I
can't uh give props to the questioners
because I just when the team pulls them
together, they don't tell me who asked
it. They just give me the show me the
questions. But thank you for everyone
who who put in questions. Anyway, um any
contra indications meaning um any uh uh
you know uh circumstances in which you
would not want to um so any
circumstances in which you would not
want to apply moisturizer, insect
repellence and or witch hazel whilst
applying sunscreen and is there any
preferred order of application? Um well
uh I mean sunscreen the cream sunscreens
actually have a moisturizer base so
presumably you wouldn't have to add
moisturizer on top of moisturizer but in
terms of insect repellent and all that
stuff. Um uh trying to think
uh yeah I mean I can't imagine it's not
like it's going to I guess if you added
a whole bunch of witch haves and it was
really sloppy you could kind of rinse
off some of the sunscreen but that
probably wouldn't happen. Probably just
rub it around good. So, uh, yeah, I I
don't think it should matter, um, in
terms of order of application.
Okay, next question. Is clothing
marketed with inherent sunscreen
absorbed? Is that absorbed when you
sweat? Um, is this UPF clothing
effective? And if so, is it effective
enough to forgo topical sunscreen while
wearing the clothing? Okay, great
question. Now, most like UPF, most sun
protective clothing is not actually
embedded with anything. It's just the
natural blocking, physical blocking. So,
like every piece of clothing, unless
it's like some super super sheer sheer
sheer, you know, lingerie or something,
every clothing has some kind of blocking
abilities. Um, but and you can tell
whether it's blocking abilities or not
by you take the clothing, you take your
shirt and you look up at the sun and if
you're like, well, try not to look up at
the sun, but you know what I mean. Like
if if light shines through, well, then
it's not very good. But uh so usually
the sun protective clothing is just a a
denser weave or a thicker material and
so you put it up and you're like, "Oh,
you can't see the sun." Well, if you
can't see the sun through the clothing,
it's it blocks the sun. Um so now is
there some clothing that actually has
some embedded chemical? If there is, I
don't think you should wear it because
then you just be then you'd be worried
about the chemical safety once again.
Um, and so the question is, well, can do
you need to worry about like you need to
put sunscreen underneath your clothing?
Um, it depends on what uh how uh
effective it is. So for anti-aging, you
need um SPF, not UPF, I don't know where
UPF came from the question here, but no,
SPF 15 for anti-aging, SPF 30 is the
recommendations for um preventing
cancer. And so if this the the clothing
is rated as SPF, you know, 10, well
then, you know, if you're going to get a
lot of direct sunlight, you want to put
some uh uh sunblock um on underneath it.
Okay. Next. I've heard some doctors,
including dermatologists, say that most
damage from skin ex most skin damage
from sun exposure is done before age 12.
Is that true? Um well I mean if you
think about that randomized control
trial where they you know had people put
more sunscreen or less sunscreen um
these were people you know I forget the
ages but middleage
um and so late in life they had this
amazing protection that they didn't show
any signs of skin aging um after daily
application of sunscreen over a four and
a half year study significantly better
than the group that only did it a few
times a week. Um so showing that you can
prevent aging at any time. Um uh and uh
the uh I mean the I mean when you're a
kid you have this remarkable capacity to
to to heal. Um but in ter I think what
you may be thinking of is in terms of
skin cancer risk. So if you had a lot of
sunburns when you were a kid, you are at
elevated risk even if the rest of your
life you are in a burka. Um and that is
um because these so-called epithelial
cancers these cancers that like linings
of organs whether it's breast glands or
colon or prostate or or skin or liver um
have uh uh it can take decades to grow.
So you know the breast cancer you get at
age you know 50 could have been from you
know some kind of teenage exposure. Um
and uh so so the there so it just it's
even more important if you got a lot of
sunburns when you were a kid. Nothing
you do about it now. You can prevent
your own kids from getting sunburn in
the first place. That's very important.
Um but you just have to be more careful
to protect your skin from the sun. And
again, there's that really hope hopeful
study showing that your body can
actually reverse some of the um
progression towards cancer just by
protecting your skin from the sun, just
from the UV rays, not even from the sun
completely. Okay, next question. Are
kids sunscreen products and sunscreen
needs any different? Does using brands
of sunscreen labeled for babies mean
that they are safer? Um,
it's all about the active ingredients,
right? We want the mineral sunscreens
regardless. Um, I don't know if there's
if I mean maybe the baby sunscreens are
higher SPF, but as long as long as the
SPF is there. Um, and you're using the
right ingredients, then that's the most
important thing. Um, and again, one
could argue it's even more important for
kids because that lifetime skin cancer
risk. That would be the only difference.
Okay. I take aanthin, four milligrams a
day, um, which is this corotenoid
pigment to help me tan naturally. Um any
thoughts on this? Um I have not looked
into aazanthin in terms of safety. Um
but there is another coronoid called
cancer zanthin. Um which uh uh causes
something called gold dust retinopathy.
Um you can actually see it uh u in the
back of your eyeball. Um uh but I have
not looked into this. So that is a
supplement I would not recommend taking.
um but have not looked into the safety
as anything. Okay. What the next
question? What is the difference between
face sunscreen and body sunscreens? Is
this just marketing or is an actual
product difference? I think it's just
marketing. Um again, what matters is the
ingredients and uh you know how potent
the the protection is um the SPF rating.
Um okay, next. What is a healthy amount
of sun exposure before needing
sunscreen? How much sun exposure per day
or month is safe to avoid any cancer?
Ideally, none. I mean, we should be
going we should be putting sunscreen
um on in the morning before we go
outside and have it on all day. Yeah. I
mean, we really should uh um try to
avoid direct sun exposure when we can.
And I said, wait a second, what about
vitamin D? Your body's super good making
vitamin D even if you wear sunscreen.
Okay. I mentioned that near next
question. I mentioned near infrared
affecting skin. Can I comment on far
infrared as in far infrared saunas? Ah
that's a great question. Um you know I
have I've
listed to look into saunas. I did one
video on saunas, but it's like, you
know, steam saunas, uh, on in terms of
detoxification from heavy metals like
lead, which is really interesting. Um,
so that's already on the site, but I
haven't looked at at infrared saunas.
Another thing I haven't looked at is
like the cold plunge stuff. There's all
these people saying there's all this
data suggesting that like exposure to
cold, cryotherapy, blah blah blah, is
helpful. Maybe, I don't know. I gotta
check out the literature. Nothing
something else on my list. Okay. Uh, so
my answer to that question is I don't
know. Great question. Next question. Can
you develop a skin a greater tolerance
for skin exposure without damage to your
skin? Well, you can certainly develop a
greater tolerance. Um, you can tan. Um,
and that's your body trying to protect
itself from the rays and so you you're
less likely to get sunburned. Um, but
that's you're you're damaging your skin
on on route. So, um, uh, I mean, yeah.
So, uh, that's not the way to do it. Um,
okay. Next. If I already had skin
cancer, am I more susceptible going forh
forward on that spot? You absolutely are
more susceptible going forward. Not
necessarily on that spot. In fact, there
shouldn't be a spot anymore. They should
have cut it out presumably. Um but
definitely in fact you're the the you're
there are randomized control trials
showing that people in exactly your
situation can significantly cut down on
your risk of subsequent cancer by using
uh daily sunscreen um uh because you're
so susceptible. Um the reason that they
choose high-risisk populations to study
is because then you don't have to do as
long a study and as large of a study,
right? I mean because you want to have
lots of skin cancer in both groups so
you can see if there's actually a
difference um in with whatever you do.
Um so uh you definitely are at higher
risk. So it's particularly important for
you to take um uh to take care. Okay,
next question. Are there particular
herbs ah that you can recommend for
being anti-kin cancer and their
properties? I've heard that green tea
has such properties. Oh well I have got
I wonder if the video is up. So, I've
got a couple videos talking about
basically things you can eat to get
sunscreen from the inside out. Um, uh,
it's a cool like there was a cool video
talking about how if you have a like how
berries like eating berries before you
go outside significantly extends the
time before you get sunburned because
the antioxidants get deposited in your
skin and protect against free radicals.
Um, whereas something like alcohol is a
prooxidant eats up your free radicals.
So I talk about how so they did like
strawberry daiquiri kind of study. Oh
no, they did uh screwdriver studies like
orange juice versus orange juice with
vodka and showed how much quicker you
sunburn after eating vodka versus um
various uh um fruits and vegetables. So
check out that video. And I know in the
book I actually talk about different
foods um that can offer that uh kind of
uh skin protection from the inside out.
nice thing about that, it kind of
boosting the natural SPF of your skin by
eating healthy foods. And I forget if
green tea it was among them. I know it's
certainly been tested. I forget which
way it went. Um, uh, the nice thing is
it's there all the time and in all the
hard-to-reach places and so you have to
think about putting it on. At the same
time, the SPF is relatively low. And so,
it's you still have to wear some
sunblock, but it it's kind of a
complimentary strategy. So, it's there
all the time and everywhere, but not
enough to offer ideal protection. So,
you add the sunblock on top. Anyway, uh
this person has some rough spots on
their face that were turned
precancerous, but after seeing
terrifying videos on of people having
skin that looked like thirdderee burns,
I did not use it. So, what are the pros
and cons of chemo cream? I have no idea.
I've never even heard about it, but
definitely something to look into.
Um, uh, you know, there's no such thing
as
safe and effective. If it's effective,
then there's some risk. The question is,
do the benefits outweigh the harms? And
that you have to figure out on a
drugby-drug basis.
All right. Are there countries
manufacturing better or more modern
sunscreen formulations than the USA
where we can purchase from? Well, you
don't need to go anywhere outside the
USA cuz you can get the mineral
sunscreens right here. Um, and so you
don't need to worry about it, right? Um,
so yeah, those are safe.
Do natural oils, avocado, peach, grape
seed providing protection against UVA
reads, UVA rays, as I've seen products
that say do.
Well, if the product says it does
something, yeah, you can never trust
anything. Now, it's possible that
something like grapeseed oil has some
antioxidants that actually may um offer
some protection, but I would highly
doubt it. I would not rely on on on
oils to protect against UV rays.
Okay. Is it okay to only use water
without soap to wash our hands after
putting on sunscreen? We don't want to
get sunscreen on our food.
So, if your uh uh sunscreen is not water
resistant, it'll wash right off just
with water, even without soap. Um, and
so you wouldn't want to do that. And if
you don't want to get sunscreen on your
food,
you don't have to eat with your hands.
That would be probably the the way to
go. Don't eat with your hands. Okay.
What do you think of the Sperty UVB
phototherapy lamp? Vitamin D lamps that
allows people to make vitamin D without
going in the sun. Um, well, I mean, if
it's turning out UV rays, then
presumably we're going to run into the
same problems. So, yeah, I I'm presuming
that's not good for skin aging or skin
cancer risk. And again, you can get all
the vitamin D you need from sun, even
when you're protecting yourself from
sun. Now, if you don't go outside, then
you're not going to get enough vitamin
D, right? I mean, they like your roof is
SPF like a million, whatever, right? you
um uh you don't get exposed inside. Um
and so if you're like you know
institutionalized
uh like you know they do these studies
of of the elderly in nursing homes they
where they never get outside they can
you can get really vitamin D deficient
in which case um you don't need a a UV
lamp to you just need to give them
vitamin D supplements. I I would
recommend 2,000 uh international units
of vitamin D3 a day uh for someone
getting inadequate sun exposure. Um and
uh I am very much an institutionalized
elder in terms of my vitamin D levels.
Um and that is because I am inside all
day reading articles so you don't have
to. Um and really don't get out much.
That'll change when I'm on the road
coming next year for the new book. But
uh yeah, so I I'm actually taking um
vitamin D every day because I get
inadequate sun exposure.
The next question, what are my vitamin D
recommendations? There you go. Okay. Is
there a sunscreen that does not have
metals in it? Oh, there's tons of
sunscreen, but we don't know if they're
safe, right? These chemical sunscreens
that don't have titanium or zinc. Um but
we don't know if they're safe because
they're absorbed into the skin. And we
know there are a couple that were
definitely not safe. Um, and so there's
lots of sunscreens without metals, but
until we know they're safe, I would not
use them. Next question. What sunscreen
options are available if your skin's
very sensitive, even a mineral
sunscreens?
Um, so when you say sensitive, usually
sensitive skin,
usually what you do with sensitive skin
is you moisturize your skin and
presumably sunscreens would be
moisturizers. Now, can people actually
develop like a titanium or zinc allergy?
That's a good question. I've never heard
of such a thing, but you can. I've
certainly heard of nickel allergy. Some
people can't handle things with the
metal nickel in it and actually run into
real problems. So, I don't know if that
would be the same skin. Very. So, I'm
not sure what you mean by very
sensitive, like you break out in a rash.
If so, I'm presuming it's not actually
the zinc of the titanium, but it's like
some all the other ingredients that they
throw in. And so you may want to try
different ones to find one that doesn't
make you break out or whatever you're
describing as being sensitive.
Next, do sunglasses without tint work
the same? What about UV blocking?
Sunglasses without a tint work the same?
We didn't actually cover the damage that
the sun can do to probably the most
sensitive tissue at all, the back of
your eye. Imagine, okay, yeah, your sun
is getting toasted, your skin's getting
toasted, but you actually have a
magnifying glass in your lenses, your
eye, which are focusing the sun's rays
right to the back of your eye. And so,
actually, cataracts are thought to be um
your body's way to protect your retina,
the yellowing of your cornea, the outer
uh part of your eye, is to block some of
those high energy blue, that high energy
blue light that is damaging your retina.
And when people get cataract surgery,
they actually can accelerate their
retinal degeneration because all of a
sudden they have more free radical
damage in the back of their eye. So what
do you do? You protect yourself. Um, you
know, there's all sorts of polarized
sunglasses which significantly cut down
on light. And you'd want them, you know,
not the little fashionable ones where
light can get in from all sides, but you
want ones that really do um cover your,
you know, uh, cover your eyes.
What's the latest research on the
possible link between sunscreen and
frontal fibrosin alopecia? I have never
heard of any such link. Um, I can pop in
into PubMed real quick just to see if
anything pops up. Okay, sunscreen.
That is not something I ran into. Well,
there there are three dozen articles.
Let us look at the latest systematic
review and meta analysis. That's the
quicky way if you just had like really a
very little amount of time to answer
some research question. You look at the
latest systematic review meta analysis.
Is that perfect? By no means. But um
it's you know if you have limited time
this is what you can do. We have limited
time. So let's do this. And what does it
say? So yeah the the use of sunscreen is
associated with a higher risk of
developing
um frontal fibrosine alipes.
Although the exact mechanism is not
clear
um they think it's uh maybe be because
of oxyenzone which is one of these
chemicals in chemical sunscreens
um uh that may be uh kind of irritating
the skin. So this may be limited to
chemical sunscreens although they didn't
look at it specifically but good
question. So this was a 2022 systematic
review in the journal of American
Academy of Dermatology suggesting that
uh yeah um and so uh um perhaps that's
another reason to stay away from
chemical sunscreens.
Uh okay. Well, let's go back to our
questions here. Um but thank you for
that question. I I I that's not
something I ran across when I was doing
because mo most I was looking at it for
aging. Um but of course the cancer
naturally popped up with that. Okay. Um,
why does squeemis cancer meaning squee
cell carcinoma show up on legs or
covered areas more than other areas? I
wonder if you're talking about melanoma.
So melanoma you can get in all sorts of
crazy areas. So there are some skin
cancers uh you know like basil cell that
show up where you'd expect them to show
up like you know top of the head or on
the nose or you know where they just get
a lot of sun exposure. other skin
cancers that can appear weird kind of
places even like you know toenails and
crazy things like that and uh may have
less to do um with uh with the UV ray
exposure. Um why does that have that
distribution? I don't think we know.
That's a good question. Is one
application in the morning sufficient
for all day protection? Um so um the uh
that study where as long as you are not
rubbing it off or wiping it off or it's
not you're not sweating so much that
you're kind of dripping it off, rinsing
it off with sweat um eight hours. It
should last eight hours. So yeah,
application in the morning um should be
sufficient unless you know you're
rolling around this the sand or
something and and it's rubbing it off.
Okay. Could I please address the effect
of sunscreen chemicals on coral reefs
and ocean life? Fantastic question. uh
is not my in my wheelhouse. So I I do
not know um what the effect of sunscreen
chemicals on coral leaf and ocean life
is. Um uh yeah, sorry. Um any foods? Oh,
any foods that can help slow skin aging?
You got it. I got a whole chapter on it.
I have a whole anti-rinkle diet section.
Um let me uh Oh, yeah. Let's let's let's
let's share it. Let's do it. Here we go.
anti-rinkle diet. Is there any way to
reduce them? Don't eat a lot of meat and
junk. Eat a lot of fruit, vegetables,
nuts. Okay, these are associations. So,
if you go to c.nfrinkle,
um there's a video how to naturally
reduce wrinkles with food, which uh um
on nutritionfacts.org right now. Um and
so there's that video. And then there's
been interventional data on almonds,
flax, seeds, soy, and mangoes. And do
they actually work when put to the test?
Yes, yes, yes, and no. So, yes to
almonds, yes to flax, yes to soy, no to
mangoes. I love mangoes. Too bad. Um, so
thank you so much everybody. Um, I hope
you learned a ton. I certainly learned a
ton as I always do when I put together
this information. And so, um, and I'm
all excited to share it and now I
finally been able to. And then uh
eventually we'll share it with the world
once all those videos eventually make it
out on nutritionfacts.org.
Visit nutritionfacts.org/audio
to see all the podcast episodes with
descriptions that include links to their
associated videos. Sources cited and
other details are available on each
video's page. Information about my
books, How Not to Die, How Not to Diet,
How Not to Age is at
nutritionfacts.org/books.
All proceeds from book sales go to
charity and sign up for our free
newsletter at
nutritionfacts.org/subscribe
to stay updated on the latest byite-size
videos and articles. Nutritionfacts.org
is a science-based nonprofit and
everything on the website is free. There
are no ads, no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks, strictly non-commercial,
not selling anything. just put it up as
a public service, as a labor of love, as
a tribute to my grandmother whose own
life was saved with evidence-based
nutrition. Thanks for listening.